Register of the Haydon L. Boatner Papers, 1932-1975.
Hoover Institution Archives
Haydon L. Boatner Papers
1932-1975
74020
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes (3.5 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, maps, notes, photographs, and printed matter, relating to military strategy and operations in the China-Burma-India Theater, and to the United Nations prisoner of war camps during the Korean War.
Boatner, Haydon L. (Haydon Lemaire), 1900-1977.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1974.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note.
8 October 1900 Born, New Orleans, Louisiana
1918 Enlisted, U.S. Marine Corps
1919-1920 Student, Tulane University, New Orleans, Louisiana
1920-1924 Graduate, U.S. Military Academy, West Point, New York
1930-1934 Chinese Language Student and Assistant Military Attache, American Embassy, Peking, China
1942 Promoted to Brigadier General
1942 Commanded General Stilwell's headquarters at Lashio, Burma, China-Burma-India Theater
1942 Commander, Chabua-Ledo Sector, China-Burma-India Theater
1942-1945 Chief of Staff, Chinese Army in India
1943-1945 Commanding General of Combat Troops, Ledo Sector, China-Burma-India Theater
1945 Chief of Staff, Chinese Combat Command, Kunming, China
1948-1951 Professor of Military Science and Tactics and Commandant of Cadets, A. & M. College of Texas
1951-1953 Deputy Commanding General, 2nd Division, Korea
1952 Commandant, P.O.W. Camp Koie Do, Korea (80,000 prisoners)
1952 Commandant, United Nations Prisoner of War Command, Korea (180,000 prisoners)
1952 Promoted to Major General
1952 Commanding General of Prisoners of War, Pusan
1952-1954 Deputy Commanding General, 4th Army
1957-1960 Provost Marshal General, Department of the Army, Washington, D.C.
1960 Retired as Major General
United States. Army--Officers.; China.; Korean War, 1950-1953--Prisoners and prisons.; Prisoners of war.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Burma.; World War, 1939-1945--China.; World War, 1939-1945.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1932-1974
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Bender, Roger James, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Bergin, William E., 1943
  - Binder, L. James, 1971-1972
  - Chen, Shang, 1944
  - Chesley, Ray T., 1945
  - China, Ministry of Foreign Affairs, 1932
  - Clark, Mark W., 1953
  - Collins, James L., Jr., 1974
  - Dubose, Charles G., 1945
  - Fairbank, John K., 1971
  - Ferris, B. G., 1942
  - Frank, Walter W., 1945
  - Freeman, Paul F., Jr., 1943
  - Gregory, James B., 1959
  - Hargrove, George, Jr., 1945
  - Hayer, William T., 1945
  - Houston, Robert W., 1945
  - Huffine, Fred, n.d.
  - Johnson, Harold K., 1966
  - Johnson, Nelson Trusler, 1933
  - Larson, A. V., 1945
  - Marshall, George C., 1945
  - Merrill, F. D., 1943
  - Ming, Wong Chung, 1944
  - Mitchell, John B., 1945
  - Moynahan, George F., Jr., 1945
  - The New York Times Book Review, The Editor, 1971
  - Pattison, Hal C., 1967
  - Potebnya, Orr Y., n.d.
  - Slater, V., 1944
  - Stilwell, Joseph, 1942-1944
  - Teague, Olin E., 1974
  - Tower, John G., 1970
  - Von Wechmar, Ruediger, 1963
  - Walker, Leonard F., 1974
  - Wyman, W. G., 1942
- WRITINGS, 1934-1966
  Unpublished articles, printed copies of published articles, unpublished typewritten thesis, and notes by Haydon L. Boatner, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - "Asian Teeth are Needed for Geneva Conventions," Army, January 1974. Printed photocopy. (Box 1)
  - "Books on Burma." An unpublished typewritten notebook, 1942
  - Comments on "Crisis Fleeting," by James H. Stone. An unpublished typewritten article, n.d.
  - "A Digest and Interpretation of the Cheng Wu Chi." An unpublished typewritten graduate thesis, 1934
  - "Koje," Saga, n.d., printed copy
  - "The Ledo Road Today." A typewritten and carbon copy draft for The Military Engineer, 1956
  - "Messages from Burma." Bound unpublished handwritten messages to officers in the field, 1942-1944
  - "Military Control of Riots at Koje-Do." An unpublished typewritten draft, n.d.
  - "Military Geography of Manchuria." Handwritten and typewritten notes on the history of the Manchu military, 1934
  - "Prisoners of War for Sale," The American Legion, August 1962. Printed copy. (Box 2)
  - "Truce Tent and Fighting Front." An unpublished typewritten draft, n.d.
  - "Barbara Tuchman's Stilwell and the American Experience in China. A Statement Thereon for the Record." An unpublished typewritten draft, n.d.
  - U.S. Lend-lease activities with China, 1941. Unpublished handwritten drafts.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1932-1975
  Biographical file, dispatches, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, notes, printed matter, etc., arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Biographical file (Box 2)
  - China-Burma-India Theater
    - Campaigns and strategy, 1941-1945
      - Notes on the draft history of the First Burma Campaign, including synopsis
      - Report on Second Burma Campaign, 1944-1945
      - Charts and maps
      - Charts and maps (Box 3)
    - Communications, 1942-1945
    - Japanese Operations, 1942-1945
      - Burma and Andaman Invasion Naval Operations, March 1942-April 1942. Japanese Monograph 79. Printed copy.
      - Burma Operations Record-The 15th Army Operations in Imphal Area and Withdrawal to Northern Burma. Japanese Monograph 134. Printed copy.
      - Burma Operations Record-The 33rd Army Operations. Japanese Monograph 148. Printed copy.
      - China Area Operations Record V.I. Japanese Monograph 70. Printed copy.
      - Japanese Preparation for Operations (prior to 1943). Japanese Monograph 77. Printed copy.
      - Japanese Studies in World War II (Historical Manuscript File). Japanese Monograph 57. Printed copy.
    - Medical-Health, 1942-1945 (Box 4)
      - General
      - "Accident on Trip 595," typewritten (carbon copy) report, 1943
      - "Complete report on First Medical Training Unit," 1945. Typewritten (carbon copy) report.
    - Personnel, 1942-1945
      - General
      - "Interview with Colonel W. A. Fuller, Cav. at Ramgarh," 1945
    - Supplies, 1942-1945
      - General
      - "History of Services of Supply, China-Burma- India." An unpublished (carbon copy) typescript. 1944.
    - Training, 1942-1945
      - General
      - "History of the Ramgarh Training Center, 1942-45." Unpublished typescript carbon copy.
      - "Training of the Chinese Troops, 1942-43." An unpublished typewritten report.
    - Transportation, 1942-1945
      - General
      - "Burma, The Construction of the Ledo Road, 1944." An unpublished typewritten (carbon copy) report.
    - Troops, 1942-1945
      - General
        - 1942
        - 1943-1944 (Box 5)
        - 1944-1945 (Box 6)
      - Handbook on China-United States Armed Forces in China-Burma-India. A bound volume, 1942. Printed copy.
  - Prisoners of War (Box 7)
    - Bibliography and notes
    - Charmatz, Jan P. and Harold M. Wit, "Repatriation of Prisoners of War and the 1949 Geneva Convention." Yale Law Journal, February 1953. Printed copy.
    - Haight, Gardiner M., "The Geneva Conventions in the Shadow War," U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings, 1968. Printed copy.
    - Hymoff, Edward, "The Day the Reds Humiliated Uncle Sam," True, 1961. Printed copy.
    - Joy, C. Turner, How Communists Negotiate. Typewritten draft of excerpt.
    - Lerch, Archer L., "The Army Reports on Prisoners of War." Reprinted from The American Mercury, 1945
    - Pamphlets
      - General
      - Geneva Conventions of August 12, 1949. Printed copy. (Box 8)
      - Protection of War Victims-Prisoners of War, 1949. Department of State Publication. Printed copy.
      - Termination of Captivity. Part IV, Section I. Direct Repatriation and Accommodation in Neutral Countries 1949. Printed copy.
      - United Nations Command, "Operations Instructions, Reference Enemy Prisoners of War," 1952. Printed copy.
    - Stone, Jules, "Legal Controls of International Conflict," 1954. A chapter from his published book.
  - Stilwell, Joseph W.
    - General
    - Tuchman, Barbara; Book reviews of Sand Against the Wind, and Stilwell and American Experience in China, 1911-1945, 1970.
- MISCELLANY
  Notes, memorabilia and clippings.
  - Notes, memorabilia, newspaper clippings (Box 8)
  - Notes by Haydon L. Boatner on his papers at the Hoover Institution.
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1942, 1952; 71 prints / 2 envelopes
  - 13 photographs pertaining to the medical training for enlisted men, Burma, 1942 (Envelope A)
  - 58 photographs pertaining to 1932, World War II, and the United Nations Prisoner of War Camp of the Korean War in 1952 (Envelope B)